Press Gang Printers fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
Press Gang Printers fonds
1970 - 1993
F-134
Q103825175
4.09 m of textual records and other material
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
PHYSICAL DESCRIPTION Fonds includes 2.32 m of textual records, 1.57 m of graphic material, 6.5 cm of photographic material (67 photographs, 10 negatives), 13 printing plates and 1 artifact (quilt). PHYSICAL DESCRIPTION Physical description: 15 photographs located in F-134-1-0-0-16 Physical description: 20 photographs located in F-134-1-0-0-17 Physical description: 15 photographs located in F-134-6-2-0-29 Physical description: 2 photographs located in F-134-6-4-0-32 Physical description: 1 photograph located in F-134-6-4-0-110 Physical description: 3 photographs located in F-134-6-4-0-124 Physical description: 2 photographs located in F-134-6-4-0-162 Physical description: 9 photographs located in F-134-6-4-0-145
Financial assistance for the arrangement and description of the records and production of the finding aid was generously provided by the Government of Canada through the National Archives of Canada and the Canadian Council of Archives' Control of Holdings Program.
Press Gang Printers
Press Gang Printers was a feminist printing collective operating in Vancouver from 1970 to 1993. It incorporated under British Columbia's Companies Act as Press Gang Publishers Ltd. in April 1970. The organization included both women and men until 1974, when it was established as a women-only feminist collective.
Press Gang published its first book under its own imprint in 1976, a collection of essays entitled "I'm Not Mad, I'm Angry: Women Look at Psychiatry." Over the years, printing and publishing activities increasingly diverged, and in 1982 Press Gang established a separate collective to manage the publishing operations. In 1989 the separation was completed when the two collectives formally became distinct legal and corporate entities, Press Gang Printers Ltd. and Press Gang Publishers Feminist Cooperative. The two organizations, however, remained closely associated and continued to operate out of the same premises -- 603 Powell Street, where the shop was established in 1978, after four years in its previous location at 821 East Hastings Street.
Politics were central to Press Gang Printers' mandate. It was an active participant in North American feminist networks, including the British Columbia Federation of Women (BCFW). It provided training and opportunities for women in a trade traditionally dominated by men, and it participated in the labour movement, particularly after 1989 when the collective unionized, joining the Communications Workers of America, Local 226. Press Gang maintained a policy of rejecting material deemed sexist or racist. Its clients were primarily local feminist, radical, activist and community groups, and, especially in the early years, it often printed material that mainstream shops would not accept.
Throughout its existence Press Gang Printers remained a collective, though its organizational structure evolved as it shifted from volunteer to paid labour, with increasing specialization and professionalism, and unionization. During the late 1980s changes in printing technology, free trade, the restructuring of the print industry, and growing competition from larger print shops created an increasingly difficult business environment. The collective survived a fiscal crisis in 1992, but in 1993, under a debt load greater than the total value of the company, Press Gang Printers was forced to cease operations.
Articles and other materials relating to Press Gang Printers' history are included in the appendix to this finding aid (hard copy version only, available in the Archives Reading Room).
published
Full
Revised
Title of the fonds is based on the name of its creator.
The fonds consists primarily of records relating to the business activities of Press Gang Printers; it also includes some records arising from the collective's participation in the British Columbia Federation of Women. Activities and events documented include incorporation, the evolution of Press Gang's organizational structure, and the separation of the printing and publishing operations; collective and committee meetings; administration and unionization; financial management, grant and loan applications, and fundraising; liaison with other organizations in the women's movement and in other social movements; production and press work; marketing and promotion; and the financial difficulties leading to the closure of Press Gang in 1993.
Record types includes articles of incorporation; correspondence and reports; meeting agendas, minutes and supporting papers; collective agreements; photographs; ledgers, financial statements, income tax returns, and annual reports; printing samples (newsletters, newspapers, leaflets, brochures, posters, cards and other graphical material); production logbooks and customer accounts; and a Press Gang quilt.
The material was arranged by the archivist, following the main file groupings established by the records creator.
Graphic materials; Artefacts; Photographic materials; Textual records; Communications; Women
The records were donated to the Simon Fraser University Archives by Press Gang Printers in 2002.
All accessions have been processed as of March 2006. No further accruals are expected.
For material relating to the publishing collective (separated in 1989), see the finding aid to the Press Gang Publishers fonds (F-184).
Some files may contain personal or confidential information. Access to these files may be restricted as stipulated by Archives policy or the donor. Files marked 'pending review' must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release, and as a result of the review access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
File and item lists are available. As of March 2006 all publications and newspapers originally listed as files have been described at the item level.
Articles and other materials relating to Press Gang Printers history are included in the appendix (hard copy version of the finding aid only, available in the Archives Reading Room).
- Organization and administration files, 1970 - 1993; F-134-1; 23 cm of textual records 35 photographs 10 negatives 1 artifact; Physical description: 15 photographs located in F-134-1-0-0-16 Physical description: 20 photographs located in F-134-1-0-0-17
  published
  Series consists of records relating to the internal organization of Press Gang Printers. Activities, events and topics documented include incorporation, the separation of the printing and publishing collectives, collective structure and history, office administration, and unionization. Records include correspondence, reports, articles and papers, resolutions, licenses, photographs, logbooks, and agreements.
  Files are arranged alphabetically by file title.
  Some files may contain personal or confidential information. Access to these files may be restricted as stipulated by Archives policy or the donor. Files marked 'pending review' must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release, and as a result of the review access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
  A file list is available.
  - Press Gang quilt, [198-?]; F-134-1-0-0-0-1 (Artifact box - large 134-34)
    Artefacts
    Open
    Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-134-item1.
  - Agreement, 1991; F-134-1-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 134-1)
    Textual records
    Pending review
  - Annual reports and resolutions, 1970 - 1991; F-134-1-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 134-1)
    Open, reading room
    Reviewed for access (Dec 12, 2023) – File includes records that contain some individuals' personal contact information. File can be accessed in the Archives' reading room, but will be redacted in any digital access copies made by Archives.
  - Articles of association, 1970 - 1974; F-134-1-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 134-1)
  - Articles of incorporation, 1992 - 1993; F-134-1-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 134-1)
  - Collective, 1977; F-134-1-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 134-1)
    Restricted in part
  - Collective, 1982; F-134-1-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 134-1)
  - Collective, 1988 - 1990; F-134-1-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 134-1)
  - Collective, 1992; F-134-1-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 134-1)
  - History, 1981 - 1991; F-134-1-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 134-1)
  - History - Kinesis articles, 1993; F-134-1-0-0-10
  - Incorporation / Co-op holding company, 1987; F-134-1-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 134-1)
  - Licenses and certificates, 1987 - 1993; F-134-1-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 134-1)
  - Logbook, 1973; F-134-1-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 134-1)
  - Logbook, 1989; F-134-1-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 134-1)
  - Name change, 1989; F-134-1-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 134-2)
  - Photographs, 1986; F-134-1-0-0-16 (Archival box - small 134-33)
    6 negatives; 15 photos.
    Textual records; Photographic materials
  - Photographs, 1989 - 1992; F-134-1-0-0-17 (Archival box - small 134-33)
    4 negatives; 20 photos.
  - Separation, 1989 - 1990; F-134-1-0-0-18 (Archival box - standard 134-2)
  - Shareholders agreement, 1988 - 1990; F-134-1-0-0-19 (Archival box - standard 134-2)
  - Union, 1989 - 1992; F-134-1-0-0-20 (Archival box - standard 134-2)
  - Union, 1989 - 1993; F-134-1-0-0-21 (Archival box - standard 134-2)
  - Union - Collective Agreement, 1993; F-134-1-0-0-22 (Archival box - standard 134-2)
  - Union - Communications Workers of America, 1989; F-134-1-0-0-23 (Archival box - standard 134-2)
- Meeting agendas, minutes and supporting papers, 1973 - 1993; F-134-2; 29 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to meetings of the Press Gang Printers collective and its committees, including general staff meetings, general collective meetings, business meetings, and meetings of the Finance Committee, Sales Committee, Ladies Auxiliary, and the Publishing Collective before its separation from the Printers. Records include agendas, minutes, correspondence, reports, financial statements, planning documents and other supporting papers.
  For other material relating to the publishing collective, see the finding aid to the Press Gang Publishers fonds (F-184).
  - Business Meeting, 1987 - 1993; F-134-2-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 134-2)
  - Finance Committee, 1984 - 1986; F-134-2-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 134-2)
  - Finance Committee, 1990 - 1992; F-134-2-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 134-2)
  - General Collective Meeting, 1978; F-134-2-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 134-3)
  - General Collective Meeting, 1978 - 1979; F-134-2-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 134-3)
  - [General Collective Meeting], 1980; F-134-2-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 134-3)
  - General Collective Meeting, 1982; F-134-2-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 134-3)
  - General Collective Meeting, 1983 - 1984; F-134-2-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 134-3)
  - General Collective Meeting, 1987 - 1990; F-134-2-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 134-3)
  - General Collective Meeting, 1987 - 1992; F-134-2-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 134-3)
  - General Collective Meeting, 1993; F-134-2-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 134-3)
  - General Collective Meeting - notes, [198-?]; F-134-2-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 134-3)
  - Ladies Auxiliary, 1984 - 1985; F-134-2-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 134-3)
  - Publishing Collective, 1977 - 1979; F-134-2-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 134-3)
  - Publishing Collective, 1980; F-134-2-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 134-3)
  - Publishing Collective, 1987 - 1989; F-134-2-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 134-3)
  - Sales Committee, 1985 - 1993; F-134-2-0-0-17 (Archival box - standard 134-3)
  - Staff Meetings, May 1973 - January 1974; F-134-2-0-0-18 (Archival box - standard 134-3)
  - Staff Meetings, December 1975 - June 1977; F-134-2-0-0-19 (Archival box - standard 134-3)
  - Staff Meetings, June 1977 - April 1978; F-134-2-0-0-20 (Archival box - standard 134-3)
  - Staff Meetings, April 1978 - July 1979; F-134-2-0-0-21 (Archival box - standard 134-4)
  - Staff Meetings, August 1979 - August 1980; F-134-2-0-0-22 (Archival box - standard 134-4)
  - Staff Meetings, September 1980 - October 1982; F-134-2-0-0-23 (Archival box - standard 134-4)
  - Staff Meetings, November 1982 - February 1984; F-134-2-0-0-24 (Archival box - standard 134-4)
  - Staff Meetings, March 1984 - January 1985; F-134-2-0-0-25 (Archival box - standard 134-4)
  - Staff Meetings, April 1985 - February 1986; F-134-2-0-0-26 (Archival box - standard 134-4)
  - Staff Meetings, February 1986 - April 1987; F-134-2-0-0-27 (Archival box - standard 134-4)
  - Staff Meetings, April 1988 - April 1990; F-134-2-0-0-28 (Archival box - standard 134-4)
  - Staff Meetings, April 1990 - June 1992; F-134-2-0-0-29 (Archival box - standard 134-4)
- Financial records, 1970 - 1993; F-134-3; 62 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to the management of Press Gang Printers' finances. Activities, events and topics documented include accounts payable, accounts receivable, payroll, grant and loan applications, income and sales tax, analyses of Press Gang's finances, and the sale of assets to the publishing collective on separation. Records include journals, ledgers and ledger cards; correspondence, reports and financial statements; application forms and agreements; and income tax returns.
  For material relating to fundraising, see series F-134-7, "Promotion, marketing and fundraising files."
  - Account book, 1989 - 1991; F-134-3-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 134-5)
  - Account book - accounts receiveable and accounts payable, 1990 - 1992; F-134-3-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 134-5)
  - Account book - accounts receiveable and accounts payable, 1991; F-134-3-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 134-5)
  - Accounts payable, 1981 - 1987; F-134-3-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 134-5)
  - Accounts payable, 1984 - 1989; F-134-3-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 134-5)
  - Accounts receiveable, vol. 1, 1981 - 1987; F-134-3-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 134-6)
  - Accounts receiveable, vol. 2, 1981 - 1987; F-134-3-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 134-6)
  - Accounts receiveable, 1985; F-134-3-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 134-6)
  - Accounts receiveable, vol. 1, 1987 - 1989; F-134-3-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 134-6)
  - Accounts receiveable, vol. 2, 1987 - 1989; F-134-3-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 134-6)
  - Correspondence - CCEC Credit Union, 1978 - 1980; F-134-3-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 134-6)
  - Financial analysis, vol. 1, 1988 - 1989; F-134-3-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 134-7)
  - Financial analysis, vol. 2, 1988 - 1989; F-134-3-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 134-7)
  - Financial report, 1975 - 1976; F-134-3-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 134-7)
  - Financial statements, vol. 1, 1978 - 1992; F-134-3-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 134-7)
  - Financial statements, vol. 2, 1978 - 1992; F-134-3-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 134-7)
  - General journal, 1984 - 1989; F-134-3-0-0-17 (Archival box - standard 134-7)
  - General journal, 1991; F-134-3-0-0-18 (Archival box - standard 134-7)
  - General journal, 1992; F-134-3-0-0-19 (Archival box - standard 134-7)
  - General journal, 1993; F-134-3-0-0-20 (Archival box - standard 134-7)
  - General ledger, 1988 - 1989; F-134-3-0-0-21 (Archival box - standard 134-8)
  - General ledger, 1990 - 1991; F-134-3-0-0-22 (Archival box - standard 134-8)
  - General ledger - ledger cards, 1984; F-134-3-0-0-23 (Archival box - standard 134-8)
  - General ledger - ledger cards, 1984 - 1988; F-134-3-0-0-24 (Archival box - standard 134-8)
  - General ledger - ledger cards, 1985 - 1987; F-134-3-0-0-25 (Archival box - standard 134-8)
  - Grant application - Local Initiatives Program, 1975; F-134-3-0-0-26 (Archival box - standard 134-8)
  - Grant application - Local Initiatives Program, 1977; F-134-3-0-0-27 (Archival box - standard 134-8)
  - Income tax returns, 1978 - 1982; F-134-3-0-0-28 (Archival box - standard 134-8)
  - Income tax returns, 1982 - 1989; F-134-3-0-0-29 (Archival box - standard 134-8)
  - Income tax returns, 1990 - 1993; F-134-3-0-0-30 (Archival box - standard 134-8)
  - Lease, 1978 - 1992; F-134-3-0-0-31 (Archival box - standard 134-8)
  - Loans - agreements, 1986 - 1989; F-134-3-0-0-32 (Archival box - standard 134-9)
  - Loans - agreements, 1986 - 1993; F-134-3-0-0-33 (Archival box - standard 134-9)
  - Loans - application, 1982 - 1983; F-134-3-0-0-34 (Archival box - standard 134-9)
  - Loans - application, 1986; F-134-3-0-0-35 (Archival box - standard 134-9)
  - Loans - CCEC, 1984; F-134-3-0-0-36 (Archival box - standard 134-9)
  - Loans - CCEC line of credit, 1990 - 1991; F-134-3-0-0-37 (Archival box - standard 134-9)
  - Loans - CCEC press loan, 1991 - 1993; F-134-3-0-0-38 (Archival box - standard 134-9)
  - [Loans - close down correspondence], 1993; F-134-3-0-0-39 (Archival box - standard 134-9)
  - Loans - publishing loan payment forms, 1987 - 1988; F-134-3-0-0-40 (Archival box - standard 134-9)
  - Loans - short term loans, 1981 - 1982; F-134-3-0-0-41 (Archival box - standard 134-9)
  - Loans - short term loans, 1988 - 1989; F-134-3-0-0-42 (Archival box - standard 134-9)
  - Payroll, vol. 1, 1990 - 1992; F-134-3-0-0-43 (Archival box - standard 134-9)
  - Payroll, vol. 2, 1990 - 1992; F-134-3-0-0-44 (Archival box - standard 134-9)
  - Sales tax - FST, 1989 - 1991; F-134-3-0-0-45 (Archival box - standard 134-9)
  - Sales tax - GST, 1990 - 1993; F-134-3-0-0-46 (Archival box - standard 134-9)
  - Separation of businesses, 1989; F-134-3-0-0-47 (Archival box - standard 134-9)
  - Shares, 1970; F-134-3-0-0-48 (Archival box - standard 134-9)
- Correspondence and subject files, 1970 - 1992; F-134-4; 52 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to Press Gang Printers' involvement in feminist and other social movements. Activities, events and topics documented include abortion, lesbian rights, unionism, political correspondence and letters of support, conferences, and liaison with other organizations. Records include correspondence, reports and photographs; reference material collected by Press Gang, including publications, newspapers, newsletters, and brochures; conference material; and notes and other working papers.
  File and item lists are available.
  - Abortion, 1977 - 1980; F-134-4-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 134-10)
  - Alternative Community Group: An Alternative Community (newspaper), 1974; F-134-4-0-0-2 (Newspaper box 134-29)
    - An Alternative Community, 1974; F-134-4-0-0-2-1 (Newspaper box 134-29)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-134-item2.
  - Association of College and University Employees: AUCE Anchor (newsletter), 1979 - 1980; F-134-4-0-0-3 (Newspaper box 134-29)
    - AUCE Anchor, vol. 5 no. 6, June 1979; F-134-4-0-0-3-1 (Newspaper box 134-29)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-134-item3.
    - AUCE Anchor, vol. 5 no. 6, June 1979; F-134-4-0-0-3-2 (Newspaper box 134-29)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-134-item4.
    - AUCE Anchor, vol. 5 no. 7, September 1979; F-134-4-0-0-3-3 (Newspaper box 134-29)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-134-item5.
    - AUCE Anchor, vol. 5 no. 7, September 1979; F-134-4-0-0-3-4 (Newspaper box 134-29)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-134-item6.
    - AUCE Anchor, vol. 5 no. 8, October 1979; F-134-4-0-0-3-5 (Newspaper box 134-29)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-134-item7.
    - AUCE Anchor, vol. 5 no. 9, December 1979; F-134-4-0-0-3-6 (Newspaper box 134-29)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-134-item8.
    - AUCE Anchor, vol. 6 no. 1, March 1980; F-134-4-0-0-3-7 (Newspaper box 134-29)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-134-item9.
    - AUCE Anchor, vol. 6 no. 2, May 1980; F-134-4-0-0-3-8 (Newspaper box 134-29)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-134-item10.
    - AUCE Anchor, vol. 6 no. 3, August 1980; F-134-4-0-0-3-9 (Newspaper box 134-29)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-134-item11.
  - Black Lesbian Newsletter, 1982; F-134-4-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 134-10)
  - Branching Out (magazine), 1977; F-134-4-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 134-10)
  - Broadside (newspaper), 1983; F-134-4-0-0-6 (Newspaper box 134-29)
    - Broadside: A Feminist Review, vol. 4 no. 7, May 1983; F-134-4-0-0-6-1 (Newspaper box 134-29)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-134-item12.
  - Broomstick (magazine), 1980; F-134-4-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 134-10)
  - Calgary Women's Newspaper, 1976; F-134-4-0-0-8 (Newspaper box 134-29)
    - Calgary Women's Newspaper, vol. 2 no. 7, July 1976; F-134-4-0-0-8-1 (Newspaper box 134-29)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-134-item13.
    - Calgary Women's Newspaper, vol. 2 no. 12, December 1976; F-134-4-0-0-8-2 (Newspaper box 134-29)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-134-item14.
    - Calgary Women's Newspaper, vol. 5 no. 9, September 1979; F-134-4-0-0-8-3 (Newspaper box 134-29)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-134-item15.
  - Canada Manpower demonstration, 1975; F-134-4-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 134-10)
  - Canadian Women's Educational Press, 1971; F-134-4-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 134-10)
  - Children, 1974 - 1975; F-134-4-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 134-10)
  - Chile, 1977; F-134-4-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 134-10)
  - Clearing House for Feminist Media, 1976; F-134-4-0-0-13 (Newspaper box 134-29)
    - Clearing House for Feminist Media, 1976; F-134-4-0-0-13-1 (Newspaper box 134-29)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-134-item16.
  - Community Congress for Economic Change credit union, 1975 - 1977; F-134-4-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 134-10)
  - Correspondence, 1972 - 1974; F-134-4-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 134-10)
  - Correspondence - Schroeder, 1974; F-134-4-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 134-10)
  - Correspondence - international, 1976 - 1981; F-134-4-0-0-17 (Archival box - standard 134-10)
  - Correspondence, 1976 - 1985; F-134-4-0-0-18 (Archival box - standard 134-10)
  - Correspondence - political, 1976 - 1985; F-134-4-0-0-19 (Archival box - standard 134-10)
    Open with enclosures
    Reviewed for access (Dec 7, 2023) – The bulk of the file is open. However, it includes a small number of documents (1) that contain the personal information of identifiable individuals (medical/psychological history). Restricted documents have been removed (enclosed); the rest of the file is open. Enclosed records may be accessed under a Research Agreement; consult the reference archivist for more information.
  - Correspondence - policy letters, 1981 - 1986; F-134-4-0-0-20 (Archival box - standard 134-10)
  - Correspondence, 1983; F-134-4-0-0-21 (Archival box - standard 134-10)
  - Correspondence - political, 1986 - 1990; F-134-4-0-0-22 (Archival box - standard 134-10)
  - Correspondence, 1986 - 1991; F-134-4-0-0-23 (Archival box - standard 134-10)
  - Correspondence, 1986 - 1992; F-134-4-0-0-24 (Archival box - standard 134-10)
  - Country Women (magazine), 1975 - 1976; F-134-4-0-0-25 (Newspaper box 134-29)
    - Country Women, vol. 14, February 1975; F-134-4-0-0-25-1 (Newspaper box 134-29)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-134-item17.
    - Country Women, vol. 21, September 1976; F-134-4-0-0-25-2 (Newspaper box 134-29)